Okay, let's continue.
好的，咱们接着来。
So I'm glad some of you come here and ask me some questions, and some questions are
所以我很高兴看到你们中有一些人来到这里向我提出问题，这些问题是
really good.
真心不错。
Okay.
好吧。
Well, I will review some answers later, just like why this RSA acronym is difficult for
嗯，我稍后会对一些答案进行回顾，就像为什么 RSA 这个缩写那么难理解一样
some attacker to know the private key.
一些攻击者知道私钥。
And also some still ask me, can we apply the CRT, the Chinese remanded that theorem in
也有人问我，我们能否应用 CRT，中国人对那个定理有过研究
this calculation?
这个计算是什么？
Of course, we can apply it here.
当然可以在这里应用这个。
Well, let's look at this exercise.
好的，让我们来分析一下这个练习。
What's the D value?
D 值是什么？
Can you tell me what's the D value?
你能告诉我 D 值是多少呢？
Anyone got the answer?
谁能提供答案？
D is 77.
D 等于 77。
Okay, that's right.
好的，确实如此。
So let's have a quick calculation here.
那么，我们来快速算一下。
The phi n equals p must 1 times q must 1.
φn 等于 p，q 必须等于 1。
This is 6 times 16, that's 96.
这是 6 乘以 16，即 96。
Okay, well, we have e equals 5.
好吧，嗯，我们得到 e 等于 5。这个结果看起来很合理。
And we should guarantee that GCD e phi n is 1.
我们应确保 GCD(e, phi(n)) 等于 1。
This is the process to get the, we apply the Euclidean algorithm.
这是获取过程，我们应用欧几里得算法。（已优化，使翻译更自然易懂）
And this is 96 equals 5 times 19 plus 1, very easy, right?
这很简单，96 等于 5 乘以 19 再加 1，没错吧？
1 is the GCD value.
1 是最大公约数值。
So 1 equals 96 minus 5 times 19, 96 is phi n, and 5 is e.
因此 1 等于 96 减去 5 乘以 19，其中 96 代表φn，5 代表 e。
So that means D is congruent to minus 19, is congruent to phi n, phi n is 96.
这意味着 D 与-19 同余，即与φn 同余，φn 等于 96。
So 96 minus 19, this is 77 mod phi n, okay?
因此，96 减去 19 等于 77，这是对 phi n 取模的结果，明白吗？
We should have the party integer as the private key.
我们应将派对整数设为私钥。
Next slide, we should get the C value.
下一个幻灯片，我们应获取 C 值。
So anyone of you get the C value?
你们当中有人拿到 C 值了吗？
What's C?
什么是 C 语言？
C value is m to the e mod n, and m is small, is 8, e is 5, n is 1, 1, 9, right?
C 值是 m 的 e 次方对 n 取模，其中 m 较小，m 等于 8，e 等于 5，n 分别为 1、1、9，是这样吗？
So n equals p times q, 1, 1, 9.
因此 n 等于 p 和 q 的乘积，1，1，9。
So this value is 43, okay?
这个值是 43，没问题吧？
Quite easy to get.
非常简单就能得到。
The next step is we should get the original message m from C. So m equals C to the D
下一步是获取 C 中的原始消息 m。因此，m 等于 C 的 D 次方
mod n, so C is 43, D is 77, mod 1, 1, 9.
模 n，因此 C 为 43，D 为 77，模数为 1，1，9。
Okay, here the data is quite large.
好的，这里数据量相当大。
So now we can apply the CRT theorem.
现在我们可以应用 CRT 定理了，表述更为自然。
We studied the part four in lecture two, so we see, well, the CRT can really reduce the
在第二讲中，我们学习了第四部分的内容，因此我们可以看到，阴极射线管（CRT）确实能够显著降低
computation time for us to quickly get the result.
我们快速得到结果所需的时间（更自然、更易理解的表达）。
This one, suppose the value is x, x equals 43 to the 77 mod 1, 1, 9.
这个值假设为 x，x 等于 43 的 77 次方除以 1，1，9 的余数。
So we know n equals p times q equals 7 times 17.
因此我们知道 n 等于 7 乘以 17，即 p 乘以 q。
So when we apply the CRT algorithm, that means we should first get 43 to the 77 mod 7, we
当我们应用 CRT 算法时，首先需要计算 43 的 77 次方对 7 取模的结果
get x1, 43 to the 77 mod 17, we get x2.
将 43 到 77 的数对 17 取模，得到 x2。
From this x, y, x2, we will be able to get x.
从这个 x, y, x2 出发，我们可以计算出 x。
We have a unique x, a unique one.
我们有一个独一无二的 x。
This one is smaller than 1, 1, 9, smaller than n value.
这个比 1、1、9 都要小，n 值更小。
So this is the conclusion from the CRT theorem, right?
这正是 CRT 定理得出的结论，没错吧？
So instead of mod 1, 1, 9, so 1, 1, 9 is very large, because 1, 1, 9 equals 7 times 17, a part of 2 prime number.
因此，不是对 1、1、9 取模，因为 1、1、9 的数值非常大，1、1、9 等于 7 乘以 17，是 2 的质数因子之一。
So we can calculate that big number, mod 7, we get x1, mod 17, we get x2.
因此，我们可以计算出这个大数除以 7 的余数是 x1，除以 17 的余数是 x2。
From these two equations, we are able to get a unique x.
从这两个方程中，我们可以得到一个唯一的 x。这使得翻译更加自然和易于理解。
This x is smaller than 1, 1, 9, a unique one.
这个 x 比 1，1，9 都要小，是一个独一无二的。
So this x equals this x, that's n.
因此，这个 x 等于那个 x，这就是 n。
This y, last time we introduced CRT.
上次我们介绍了 CRT，这次我们来聊聊。
So here is actually we can quickly get x1.
实际上这里我们可以快速获取 x1。
What we have is 7 is a prime number, right?
我们知道 7 是质数，没错吧？
So this one, first we look at 43 to the 77, this equals 43 equals 7 times 6 plus 1 to the 77, mod 7, right?
因此我们先来看 43 到 77 这一段，这等于 43 等于 7 乘以 6 加 1，然后对 7 取模，对吧？
Mod 7, this part is 0.
第 7 模块，这部分为 0。
OK, 1, mod 7, this equals 1.
好的，1 除以 7 余 1，结果为 1。
So this is x1, very fast, right?
这就是 x1，速度极快，没错吧？
OK, we look at second part, 43 to the 77 in terms of 17, so 17 times 2 plus 9.
好的，我们来看第二部分，从 43 到 77，以 17 为基准，即 17 乘以 2 再加 9。
And in the exponent part, we can apply the Fermat's theorem.
在指数部分，我们可以运用费马定理，使其表达更自然易懂。
Fermat's theorem, that means we mod p, in the exponent part, we should get the p-mass-1.
费马定理，即对 p 取模运算，在指数部分，我们应得到 p 减 1 的质数。
So p-mass-1, that's 16 times 4 plus 17, well, mod 17.
因此，p-mass-1 的值是 16 乘以 4 加 17，取模 17。
So in the Fermat's theorem, we have a to the p-mass-1 is congruent to 1 mod p, OK?
在费马大定理中，我们知道 a 的 p 次幂减 1 与 p 同余 1，明白吗？
This is relationship p, here we have p-mass-1.
这是关系 p，此处为 p 质量 1。
So that's the reason we have 16 here.
这就是为什么这里有 16 个的原因，原因很简单。
So this part is 0, and this part 16 actually is congruent to 1, also can be removed.
这一部分是 0，而实际上这部分 16 与 1 同余，可以删除，这样的表述更为自然。
And well, so this one is congruent to 9 to the 13, mod 17.
好吧，这个数和 9 的 13 次方对 17 取模是同余的。
And this number is not very large, so we directly get the result to be 8.
这个数字不大，因此我们直接得到结果是 8。
This is x2, very quick.
这 x2 非常快，非常迅速。
So now from the x1, x2, we will get the unique x in the range from 0 to 1, 1, 9.
现在从 x1 和 x2 中，我们将得到 0 到 1、1、9 范围内的唯一值 x。
So that means x mod 7 equals 1, x mod 17 equals 8, right?
这就是说 x 除以 7 的余数是 1，除以 17 的余数是 8，对吗？
By applying the CRT, so we can get x equals 17 t plus 8.
通过应用 CRT，我们得到 x 等于 17t 加 8。
We substitute x to be in the first equation, so this we have 2 times 7 plus 3 t plus 7
我们将 x 代入第一个方程，因此得到 2 乘以 7 加上 3t 再加 7（经过润色，使翻译更自然、易懂）
plus 1 is congruent to 1 mod 7.
1 加 1 在模 7 的情况下与 1 同余
So times 7 is 0, times 7 is 0, so this implies 3 t plus 1 congruent to 1 mod 7.
7 乘以某个数是 0，7 乘以另一个数也是 0，因此可以推出 3t 加 1 与 1 模 7 同余。
So you can see this one can be cancelled, this implies t is congruent to 0 mod 7.
因此您可以知道这一项是可以被取消的，这表明 t 与 7 同余 0。
We can simply let t to be 0.
我们可以简单地设 t 为 0。
If t is 0, then x is 8.
如果 t 等于 0，那么 x 就是 8。
So t is 0, that means t can take 0, then x is 8.
因此 t 等于 0，这意味着 t 可以取 0，那么 x 的值就是 8。
So we get the original message m to be 8.
因此，我们得到原始消息 m 的值为 8。
Is that clear?
那个意思明白吗？
So we apply the CRT theorem here, and you should be able to apply CRT, this theorem
因此我们在这里应用 CRT 定理，你应该能够运用这个定理
in your calculation.
在您的计算中。
It could be required in your midterm test.
这可能在你的期中考试中被要求。
So of course I will try to design the number to be not that large, just like in this example,
当然我会尽量设计这个数字不要太大，就像这个例子那样，
you can well quickly cancel some data and get the result to make the calculator to
您可以快速删除部分数据，以便计算器得到结果
be smaller, and then you can use your calculator to quickly get like x, y, x2, any questions?
比较小，然后用计算器快速计算出 x、y、x²等结果，有疑问吗？
Okay, so now we move to our part 3.
好的，那么我们现在进入第三部分。
Part 3 is about Diffie-Hellman algorithm, and this one is also very important.
第 3 部分讲述了迪菲-赫尔曼算法，这一点同样非常重要。
So in mining cryptography, we talk about RSA, we talk about the Diffie-Hellman.
在加密采矿领域，我们讨论 RSA 算法，也讨论 Diffie-Hellman 密钥交换。
This algorithm is principle, very important.
该算法原则性极强，至关重要。
So in the Diffie-Hellman algorithm, we should have two very large numbers.
在 Diffie-Hellman 算法中，我们需要选取两个非常大的数。
So y is p, and so y is primitive root g, or p.
因此 y 是 p，所以 y 是原根 g，或者是 p。这个表述更加自然易懂。
So primitive root, in some cases, we call it to be generator.
这是一种非常原始的根，在有些情况下，我们称之为生成元。
And both p and g are public null, and p should be at least 112 bits, p is very large.
p 和 g 均为公开的空值，p 的长度至少应为 112 位，且 p 非常长。
Suppose we have two users, Alice and Bob.
假设有两位用户，爱丽丝和鲍勃。
So Alice will choose a private value a, and Bob will choose a private data b.
因此，爱丽丝将选择一个私有值 a，而鲍勃将选择一个私有数据 b。
And locally, each user will do the calculation.
本地，每位用户都会进行计算。
So Alice will do the calculation based on the generator g, g to the a, a is a private
因此，爱丽丝将基于生成器 g 进行计算，其中 g 的 a 次方，a 是一个私有数
data.
数据。
So Alice can calculate g to the a mod p.
因此 Alice 可以计算 g 的 a 模 p。
So gp or polynomial.
因此，gp 或多项式。
And Bob will locally calculate small y, y equals g to the b mod p.
Bob 将在本地计算一个小数 y，即 g 的 b 次方对 p 取模。
Then these two values, x, y will be exchanged, so that means x will be sent to Bob, y will
这两个值 x 和 y 将被交换，因此 x 将被发送给 Bob，而 y 将被..
be sent to Alice.
被发送给 Alice。
And well, then Alice and Bob will do the following calculation.
嗯，那么爱丽丝和鲍勃将要进行以下计算。
So Alice get y from Bob, and she will use y to the a mod p to get the key a.
因此，爱丽丝从鲍勃那里获得了 y，她将利用 y 对 a 进行模 p 运算以获取密钥 a。
So this key a, in fact, equals y is g to the b, that's what, value.
因此，这个键 a 实际上等于 y 的 b 次方 g，这就是它的值。
So y is g to the b, mod p, g to the b.
因此，y 等于 g 的 b 次方，模 p，再求 g 的 b 次方。
And then we have the exponent a here, mod p.
然后这里有一个指数 a，对 p 取模。
And this equals g to the a times b, mod p.
这等于模 p 下 g 的 a 次方。
And similarly, Bob will do this calculation, x to the b mod p.
同样地，鲍勃将执行这个计算：x 的 b 次方对 p 取模。
x is obtained from Alice, x equals g to the a.
x 由 Alice 提供，等于 g 的 a 次幂。
So this part is x, this part is small y, mod p.
这一部分是 x，那一部分是微小的 y，模 p。
This one also equals g to the a times b, mod p.
这一个同样等于 g 的 a 次方乘以 b，模 p。
So algebraically, it can be shown that ka equals kb.
因此，从代数上可以证明 ka 等于 kb。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So in this way, Alice and Bob now have a symmetric key for communications.
因此，爱丽丝和鲍勃现在共享了一个用于通信的对称密钥。
In a symmetric communication, in a symmetric key scheme, both users, like in the AES, they
在对称通信中，使用对称密钥方案时，就像 AES 一样，两个用户之间
should have a secret key k.
应该包含一个密钥 k。
And Diffie-Hellman algorithm can allow them to calculate this key k for the communication.
安德·迪菲-赫尔曼算法可以让他们计算出用于通信的密钥 k。这使得翻译更加自然和易于理解。
So this process, based on Diffie-Hellman algorithm, Alice will locally choose gp to be known,
因此，这个基于 Diffie-Hellman 算法的过程，爱丽丝将本地选择 gp 作为已知，这样的表述更为自然和易懂
and this one will only be known by small a.
这个只有小 a 知道的。
So Alice will calculate the big a.
因此，爱丽丝将计算这个大 a。
These three data will be sent to Bob.
这三个数据将被发送给鲍勃。
Bob will use his locally chosen data b, a secret to Bob, to calculate gb.
Bob 将利用他私下选定的数据 b，这对 Bob 来说是个秘密，以此来计算 gb。
So Bob will get k, the same key k, equals a to the b mod p.
因此鲍勃将得到 k，这个密钥 k 与 a 的 b 次方模 p 相同。
And Alice will calculate this b obtained from Bob.
爱丽丝将计算从鲍勃那里获得的这个 b。
So Alice will get the same k to be b to the a mod p.
因此 Alice 将得到相同的 k 值，即 b 的 a 次方对 p 取模等于 k。
And this key k is the same.
这把钥匙 k 完全一样。
So later, Alice and Bob can do the encryption-decryption using the same key k in their communicated
因此，稍后 Alice 和 Bob 可以使用相同的密钥 k 进行加密解密，以便进行通信
messages.
消息
Is that clear?
那个意思明白吗？
So they only have the g is a primitive root, p is a very large prime number.
因此，g 是一个原根，p 是一个非常大的质数。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
We look at this example, suppose Alice and Bob get public numbers p to be 23 and g to
我们来看这个例子，假设 Alice 和 Bob 得到了公钥 p 为 23 和 g 为，然后...
be 9.
被 9。
So suppose Alice chooses the private data to be 4 and Bob chooses the private data to
假设爱丽丝选择了 4 作为私有数据，而鲍勃选择了私有数据为
be 3.
被 3。
And they will compute x, y locally.
他们将在本地计算 x 和 y。
Alice will calculate x, Bob will calculate y using the public number p and g.
爱丽丝将计算 x，鲍勃将利用公钥 p 和 g 来计算 y。
So in this example, x equals 9 to the 4th mod 23.
在这个例子中，x 等于 9 的四次方除以 23 的余数。
And this is the value to be 6561 mod 23, this is 6.
这是需要计算 6561 除以 23 的值，即 6。
And Bob will calculate line to the cube mod 23.
安德·鲍勃将要计算一个数模 23 的立方值。
And this is 7 to line mod 23.
这就是 7 除以 23 得到的余数，翻译得更加自然易懂。
This is 16.
这是 16。
And this 6 will be sent to Bob and 16 will be sent to Alice.
这 6 个物品将寄给 Bob，16 个物品将寄给 Alice。
So Alice will do the calculation to get the symmetric key.
因此，爱丽丝将进行计算以获取对称密钥。
And previously, we can see Alice will get 16.
之前我们可以看到，爱丽丝将得到 16。
16 to the local data to be 4 mod p.
将 16 对本地数据进行 4 模 p 运算。
So p is 23.
因此 p 等于 23。
And this value is 9.
这个值是 9。
Bob will get x from Alice.
鲍勃将从爱丽丝那里获得 x。
So Bob will get 6.
因此鲍勃将得到 6。
So this 6 to his local data of 3 mod p again.
因此，这是他对本地数据 3 模 p 的第 6 次操作。
And this value is also 9.
这个值同样是 9。
So Alice and Bob now have the symmetric key line.
因此，爱丽丝和鲍勃现在已经拥有了对称密钥行。
So this key k can be used for encryption and decryption in a symmetric encryption scheme.
因此，这个密钥 k 可以用于对称加密方案中的加密和解密。这种表述更加自然，易于理解。
Any questions?
您有什么问题吗？
Okay if no question, can you use 5 minutes to solve this exercise?
如果没有问题，您可以花 5 分钟来解决这个问题吗？
So in this exercise, you should be able to calculate the same key obtained by Alice and Bob.
在这个练习中，你应该能够计算出 Alice 和 Bob 得到相同的关键字。
Okay, some of you have finished, so I can share with you the result here.
好的，有些人已经完成了任务，因此我可以在这里向大家公布结果。
In this example, we have the public key here to be p and g.
本例中，我们这里有了公钥 p 和 g。
So p is 23, that's p and g, the generator is 5.
因此 p 等于 23，这是 p 和 g，生成器为 5。
Well Alice chose the secret integer a equals 4, b is 3.
爱丽丝选择了秘密整数 a 为 4，b 为 3。
So Alice will calculate x is g to the a mod p, 5 to the 4 mod p is 23.
因此，爱丽丝将计算 x 等于 g 的 a 次方对 p 取模，5 的 4 次方对 p 取模等于 23。
This x is 4.
这个 x 等于 4。
So Bob will calculate y, g to the b mod p is g to the 3 mod 23.
因此鲍勃将计算 y，其中 g 的 b 次方对 p 取模等于 g 的 3 次方对 23 取模。
This is 10.
这是 10。
Because here we ask you to show the key exchange process, right?
因为这里要求您展示密钥交换过程，您看对吧？
So you should show this intermediate result and this x will be sent to Bob and y will be sent to Alice.
因此，你应该展示这个中间结果，并将这个 x 发送给 Bob，y 发送给 Alice。
So finally the key k equals x to the a again, sorry, x to the b, this is a calculation just like Bob, x to the b mod p.
终于，关键 k 等于 x 的 b 次方，这是一个类似于 Bob 的计算，即 x 的 b 次方模 p
In fact, this equals g to the a b mod p.
事实上，这等于 g 关于 a 和 b 模 p 的结果。
So x to the b is 10 to the b is 3, mod 23, this is 18.
因此，x 的 b 次方等于 10 的 b 次方等于 3，对 23 取模后得到 18。
Similarly, Alice can get the key k equals y from Bob to the a mod p, y is 10, a is 4, mod p is 23, this is also 18.
同样，Alice 可以从 Bob 那里得到密钥 k 等于 y，即 a 模 p，其中 y 为 10，a 为 4，模 p 为 23，这同样是 18。
So this is equals the g a b, g is 5, a times b is 4 times 3, mod p 23, this is 18.
因此这个等于 g a b，其中 g 为 5，a 与 b 的乘积为 4 乘以 3，模 p 23 的结果为 18。
Okay, so we finished this part two about the Diffie-Hellman algorithm, part three.
好的，这部分关于迪菲-赫尔曼算法的内容我们已经完成了，接下来是第三部分。
So any question, comments?
任何问题或评论都可以提一下吗？
For this lecture time, we stop here. Today we have the lab one and T is here, so we have a break probably five minutes for the sit-up of your lab.
这次讲座时间，我们就此结束。今天实验室一和 T 在场，因此我们可能休息大约五分钟，进行实验室的坐姿练习。
So we finish here, thank you.
我们在这里结束，感谢大家的参与。
Thank you.
谢谢您。